Guide to the International Monitor Institute. Middle East videotapes, 1991-2008 RL.00606
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
International Monitor Institute. Middle East videotapes
1991-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
International Monitor Institute
RL.00606
108 Linear Feet
The non-profit agency International Monitor Institute (IMI) operated between 1993 and 2003, primarily to assist international war-crimes tribunals by collecting, indexing and organizing visual evidence of violations of international human rights law. The International Monitor Institute Records, Middle East Videotapes span the dates 1991-2008, and comprise audiovisual materials related to IMI's documentation of contemporary conflicts and human rights violations in the Middle East, including Iran, Iraq, Afghanistan, Kuwait, Israel, Palestine, and Lebanon. The collection includes footage regarding the Iranian revolution, the Kurdish genocide in Iraq and refugee populations in Lebanon, chemical warfare, the September 11, 2011 terrorist attacks on the World Trade Center, the war on terror, and the Israeli-Palestinian conflict. Also included is a Department of Air Force Series covering Operation Provide Comfort. Documentaries and news segments make up the bulk of material in this collection; news segments are predominantly from CNN, Frontline, Fox News, and Al Jazeera.
720 Items
Access Restrictions
CLOSED: Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The International Monitor Institute. Middle East videotapes were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2006-2007.
Collection Overview
The International Monitor Institute Records, Middle East Videotapes span the dates 1991-2008, and comprise audiovisual materials related to IMI's documentation of contemporary conflicts and human rights violations in the Middle East, including Iran, Iraq, Afghanistan, Kuwait, Israel, Palestine, and Lebanon. The bulk of these audiovisual materials are comprised of documentaries and news reports that cover the political climates, histories, and governmental structures of Middle-Eastern states, especially Iraq and Iran. Much of this material documents Saddam Hussein's Kurdish Genocide (al-Anfal) and his campaign against the Marsh Arabs, activities of the Iraqi secret police, and the experience of Kurdish refugees in camps such as Azerbaijani. Material also documents humanitarian relief for Kurdish refugees, including the activities of the United States military in Operation Provide Comfort. Other documentary material explores state torture and state-sponsored terrorism in Iraq, including chemical attacks and the genetic effects of chemical weapons on the population. Records further document various political and military institutions, including the Kurdistan Workers' Party (KPP), Kurdistan Democratic Party (KDP), and the Patriotic Union of Kurdistan (PUK), as well as the activity of various international organizations such as the United Nations and Amnesty International. Several documentaries examine events leading up to the Gulf War and its aftermath, the war in Beirut, the lives of Palestinian refugees in Lebanon, and rights conflicts regarding Palestinians living in Israel. Videotapes further document the Iranian revolution and post-revolution, and the fall of the Shah. The bulk of news reports were produced by CNN, Fox, Frontline, and Al-Jazeera. Coverage focuses on the September 11, 2011 attacks on the World Trade Center, as well as material on the war on terror, Osama bin Laden and Al Queda training camps. The following tapes were not transferred to the Rubenstein Library and descriptions of these tapes has been omitted from this finding aid: ME048, ME054-ME057, ME059-ME067, ME070-ME071, ME073-ME074, ME102-ME103, ME112, ME204-ME206, ME291, ME350, ME417, ME1074.Further organizational material on the Middle East can be found in the International Monitor Institute Records, also at the Rubenstein Library.
Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive.
Related Material
International Monitor Institute Records,1986-2006
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
International Monitor Institute. Burma videotapes, circa 1990-2002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
International Monitor Institute. Rwanda Videotapes and Audiotapes, 1992-1999
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
HU OSA 350, Fonds 350: Records of the International Monitor Institute
Open Society Archives, Central European University
Victims of state-sponsored terrorism -- Iraq; War on Terrorism, 2001-2009; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001; Torture -- Turkey -- Politics and government; Taliban -- Afghanistan; Gases, Asphyxiating and poisonous -- War use -- genetics; Anfal Campaign, Iraq, 1986-1989; Refugees -- Afghanistan; Lebanon -- Foreign relations -- Israel; United States -- Foreign relations -- Iran; Israel -- Foreign relations -- Palestine; Kurdistan (Iraq) -- Ethnic relations; Iran -- History; Iraq -- History; Iraq -- Chemical warfare; Iraq -- Foreign relations -- Kuwait; United States -- Foreign relations -- Iraq; Documentary films -- Iraq; Iran -- History -- Revolution, 1979; Iran-Iraq War, 1980-1988; Marsh Arabs -- Warfare, society and culture -- Environmental aspects; Oil fields -- Environmental aspects -- Kuwait; Persian Gulf War, 1991; Refugees, Kurdish; Kurds -- History -- 20th century; Petroleum -- Economic aspects -- United States; Saddam (Iraq) -- Psychology; Saddam (Iraq) -- Massacres; Qaida (Organization); Partiya Karkarên Kurdistanê; Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees -- Criticism; International Monitor Institute; Hizb al-Ba'th al-Arabi al-Ishtiraki (Iraq); Bin Laden, Osama, 1957-2011; United States. Navy -- Humanitarian Assistance -- Iraq; United States. Air Force -- Humanitarian Assistance -- Iraq
- Middle East videotapes, circa 1991-2008, 80 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Further organizational material on the Middle East can be found in the International Monitor Institute Organizational Records, also at the Rubenstein Library.
  - Frontline: Saddam's Killing Fields [1992 Mar. 31], NTSC VHS [TRT:0:58:00] (2 copies) (Box 328 and 336, Video-cassette ME001)
    Language: English
    Producer: Frontline
    Original Credits: Correspondent: Hodding Carter. Frontline Producer: Robin Parmalee
    Introduction: Interview of Kanan Makiya by Hodding Carter and his experience in Northern Iraq and his story, scenes of Saddam Hussein, raw footage of invasion of Kuwait. Main Part of tape is the American version/screening of documentary made by Northern Iraq by Gwynne Roberts and Kanan Makiya.
    See record ME017 Part 1.
    One year after the fateful Kurdish uprising, Frontline charts dissident Iraqi writer Kanan Makiya's secret return to Iraq to investigate rumors of an official extermination program aimed at the Kurds, this is called the Anfal. Makiya travels from town to town, sifting through documents, audiotapes, and video footage kept for years by the Iraqi secret police and captured by the Kurds in the uprising. The records detail the horrifying scale of the Iraqi state's routine surveillance, torture, and murder.
  - Frontline: The Gulf War, NTSC VHS [TRT:4:00:00] (Box 316: 2 copies; Box 336: 1 original) (Box 316 and 336, Video-cassette ME002)
    Producer: Co-production by Frontline/BBC
    Original Credits: Producer for Frontline: Ben Loeterman. Producer for BBC: Eammon Mathews
    Three part documentary that reconstructs the events leading up to the war, the war itself, and its aftermath. First hand accounts from major American players in the war, Generals Schwarzkopf and Powell, President Bush and other world leaders, Brent Scrowcroft, Middle East Advisor Richard Haass, Margaret Thatcher, Gorbachev, Moshe Arens, Iraqi soldiers, many American advisors and policy people, General Calvin Waller, General John Leide, General Buster Glossen, Robert Gates, Bernard Trainor, Tom Ricks (author of The Generals), General Walter Boomer, Waf iq Sammarai, General Chuck Horner, Colonel David Baker.
  - ICA Iraqi Civilian Aid - News Reports and Interviews with Dr. Shahristani, 1994 Jan. and Feb., NTSC VHS [TRT:0:22:40] (2 copies) (Box 316 and 336, Video-cassette ME003)
    Language: English/Arabic
    Producer: Various
    Original Credits: Reporter: Lyse Doucet
    Sky News Report, John Cookson reporter, report on the destruction of the Marsh Shiite's ecology by flooding the marshes leading to repression/genocide by Saddam's government, interviews with Dr. Hussein Shahrastani, human rights campaigner, 1994 Jan. 27, 2:15.
    BBC News, draining homes of Marsh Shiites, controlled flooding, draining marshes, campaign for the creation of safe havens in the south, campaign to publicize this situation, Lyse Doucet Reporter, 1994 Feb. 1.
    Channel 4 News report on altering Marsh environment, refugees from rising water, caused by Iraqi government, Kent Barker reporter, 1994 Feb. 8.
    MSC Network, Ismail al-Amin reporter, report in Arabic, interview with Dr. Shahrastani.
    Raw footage of flooding in Southern Iraq, 1994 Feb. 1; reports above seem to be taken from this documentation/footage.
  - Viewpoint '93-Saddam's Killing Fields: Part 1, Lament of the South; Part 2, Massacre in the Marshes; Part 3, Crimes Against Humanity, NTSC VHS [TRT:0:53:34] (2 copies) (Box 316 and 336, Video-cassette ME004)
    Viewpoint '93, ITV Production, Michael Wood writer/reporter, Hawaiza Marsh, Iran/Iraq Border
    Part 1: Aftermath of failed uprising, persecution of Shiites post-Gulf War, destruction of Karbala, Najaf, comparisons with Kurdish situation, interview with Dr. Ahmed Chalabi, President, Iraqi National Congress opposition party, interviews with Iraqis, interview with Laurie Mylroie, Washington Institute for Near East Policy, complicity of US troops, Schwarzkopf.
    Part 2: Anfal Massacre, scenes of torture of Kurdish civilians, Ali Hassan al-Madjid, Saddam's cousin's plan for repression/genocide, interview with Wilfred Thesiger, author of The Marsh Arabs, poisoning of the water by Iraqi troops, Max van der Stoel, UN Human Rights Special Reporter: Iraq.
    Part 3: Thaer al-Hadairi, Executive Director, Documentation Centre for Human Rights in Iraq, based in Tehran, documentation of government plan to drain marshes, Kenneth Timmerman, Special Assistant on Foreign Affairs, US Congress, duplicity of US, German companies breaking sanctions to sell equipment to Iraq, Douglas Hogg, MP, Minister of State, situation in Hawaiza Marsh.
  - UNHCR-Refugees in Azerbaijan, NTSC Beta [TRT:0:10:35] (2 copies) (Box 316 and 336, Video-cassette ME005)
    Footage of women and children speaking Turkish-Azerbaijani, discussing their experiences as refugees; also footage of children in classrooms and in apartments. Aid workers talking about the situation of refugees from the conflict in Azerbaijan and Armenia during the early 1990's.
  - UNHCR-Iraq Winter Shelter Program, NTSC Beta [TRT:0:09:10] (2 copies) (Box 316 and 336, Video-cassette ME006)
    Language: Japanese/English
    Producer: UNHCR
    United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) footage of Iraq winter shelter program for Kurdish refugees, with shots of the Japanese head of UNHCR Ogata. Footage of air drops to Kurdish refugees and the situation of Kurdish refugees following the exodus after the Uprisings following the Gulf War. Voice over in Japanese with some English and Kurdish in the background. Footage of destroyed villages and the role of the UNHCR in taking care of the Kurdish refugees in preparation for the coming winter with shots of rebuilding homes, etc. and the supplies of building materials and the Kurdish desire to rebuild and return to their homes following the crisis. Footage of winter conditions in Kurdish northern Iraq.
  - UNHCR-Kurdish Exodus, NTSC Beta [TRT:0:06:45] (2 copies) (Box 316 and 336, Video-cassette ME007)
    Language: Scandinavian?
    United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) footage - Kurdish refugees, situation of children on Iraq/Iran border, connected with the previous tape. Footage of the refugee situation, and shots of people pleading to the Western aid workers to help them during the crisis and statements by the Japanese head of UNHCR Ogata on how they can help the situation. Some air footage of the destroyed villages and some overviews of Suleimaniyya and footage of Ogata meeting with the Iranians about the refugee situation, more over head footage of the camps and Ogata touring the camps. Also some footage of Ogata meeting with the Turkish president.
  - UNHCR: Returnees in Iderat (Afghanistan), NTSC Beta [TRT:0:09:45] (2 copies) (Box 316 and 336, Video-cassette ME008)
    Language: Pashtu/Persian
    United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) footage documents the situation in Herat and the changes in the city following the return of Afghan returnees to Herat and other areas, and the basket weaving and other projects developed by the UN to help the economy and work of women in Afghanistan in the early 1990's. Interviews with various United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees aid workers and footage of the refugee camps and the city, as well as footage of classrooms, including the education of women and girls. Footage of mine clearing activities in Iran and discussion of returnees in 1992, as well as 1993-1994 in relation to attempts to plant crops and use canals where mines have been planted. Interviews with returnees.
  - The Lost Tribes, NTSC Beta [TRT:0:48:35] (2 copies) (Box 316 and 336, Video-cassette ME009)
    Language: Pashtu/English
    Producer: Oxford Ethnographic Films in association with United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees
    Original Credits: Narrated by James Mason. Produced and Directed by Andre Singer
    Documentary on the plight of Afghan refugees in Pakistan fleeing from the war with the Soviet Union. In 1984 this group was the largest refugee population in the world. Interviews with children as well as families of refugees. Also includes footage of the bureaucratic processes involved with settlement of the refugees and the translation of their conversations. Analysis of one family and their journey in terms of the tribal relations and the help that the other Pushtun families extend to one another. Interviews also with the women of the family and how they miss their homes and the conditions that they are forced to live under in exile as refugees.
  - Raw Footage with Emma Nicholson, MP on Marsh Arabs of Southern Iraq, NTSC VHS [TRT:0:44:00] (2 copies) (Box 316 and 336, Video-cassette ME010)
    Language: Arabic/English
    Producer: Raw footage for BBC
    Raw footage of marshes, interviews with marsh Arabs concerning the bombings of the marshes by Saddam Hussein and his regime and the situation in the marshes at the present time, translated into English; interviews with Emma Nicholson during her visit to the marsh Arabs and their making statements about how they need to push Saddam back out of the area and create a safe haven for Iraq; they are in the safe haven of Iran, footage of wounded men.
  - Iraq Foundation: News Report, NTSC VHS [TRT:0:02:00] (2 copies) (Box 316 and 336, Video-cassette ME011)
    Language: Arabic
    News report of torture and beatings in people's homes, scenes of men in hospital and hand amputation.
  - Part I-RAF Air Footage of Iraqi Marsh Fires, Part II-Documentary on Palestinian Collaborator and Israeli recruiter, NTSC VHS [TRT:0:45:00] (Box 316, Video-cassette ME012)
    Producer: Israel Goldvicht, October Films co-production for BBC Television. Taped off of BBC Television 2
    Part I: In vicinity of N 31 20 00 E 047 00 00, 1995 Jul. 11 and within 10km of N 31 21 00 E 047 05 00, 1995 Aug. 7.
    Part II: Story of Palestinians collaborating with the Israeli army, documentary in English, interview with Political Scientist Dr. Saleh Abdel Jawad on motives of collaborators, Meir Cohen, Israeli intelligence, recruiter of collaborators.
    Narrator: Edward Stourton, Producer: Israel Goldvicht, Director: Nick Read.
  - Saddam's Latest War-A Commentary by Michael Wood, NTSC VHS [TRT:0:56:00] (2 copies) (Box 316 and 337, Video-cassette ME013)
    Original Credits: Writer/Presenter: Michael Wood. Producer: Rebecca Dobbs, Stephan Reverand. Director: Christopher Jeans
    Remade Version of ME004 for American Television of documentary film made by Michael Wood about the situation of the Shiites and Marsh Arabs in southern Iraq following the Gulf War. Included is additional interview with Martin Indyk, U.S. Policy Advisor on the Middle East, on prosecuting Saddam Hussein for war crimes and the issue of safe havens for Southern Iraq and sanctions for Iraq.
    Same documentary as ME04; see synopsis 04.
  - 60 Minutes: What is Saddam Hiding? [1997 Nov. 23], NTSC VHS [TRT:0:13:30] (2 copies) (Box 316 and 337, Video-cassette ME014)
    Producer: CBS
    Original Credits: Produced by Leslie Cockburn.
    Interview with General Wafiq Sammarahi, detailing the efforts of Saddam's regime to conceal the making of chemical and biological weapons. Sammarahi is a defector from the regime of Saddam Hussein.
  - Save Iraq's Children and International Criminal Court: The Challenge of Enforcing Human Rights Law, NTSC VHS [TRT:6:00:00] (Box 337, Video-cassette ME015)
    Original Credits: JusticeVision. 1425 W. 12th St., #262. Los Angeles, CA 90015. 213-747-6345
    Save Iraq's Children: A Rally to End the U.S./UN Embargo Against Iraq with Ramsey Clark, Kathy Kelly, Gloria La Riva, Michael Shehadeh and Rev. James Lawson, LA, CA, 1998 Mar. 7 [02:07:00].
    M.L. King Interfaith Celebration excerpt with Jesse Jackson, Blenda Wilson, and Steve Allen. Beth Hillel, Burbank, CA, 1998 Jan. 19 [01:05:00].
    Ward Valley Walking Tour, 1997 Apr. 25 [00:51:00].
    An International Criminal Court: The Challenge of Enforcing Human Rights Law with U.S. Ambassador for War Crimes David Scheffer, Happy Mutesi, Richard Dicker, Elizabeth Farr and Edwin M. Smith, LA, 1998 Feb. 26 [02:03:00].
  - Dispatches - Saddam's Secret Time-Bomb [1998 Feb. 23], PAL VHS [TRT:0:42:00] (4 copies) (Box 316, 321, 334 and 337, Video-cassette ME016)
    Producer: Roberts and Wykeham Films. For Channel Four BBC
    Original Credits: Reporter: Gwynne Roberts. Producer: Sadie Wykeham. Director: John Williams.
    Report on Halabja ten years after and the UN cover up of Western countries that supplied Saddam with chemical weapons, Professor Christine Gosdin, Liverpool University, geneticist, to study long term effects on civilians, Dr. Fouad Baban in Suleimaniyya, attack on Halabja March 1988, includes archival footage of dead during attack, footage of skin diseases and nerve diseases caused by chemical attacks, proving long term nerve damage from chemical weapons, also cancers caused by chemical, investigation of links to Gulf War syndrome, mass graves poisoning the water tables and the land, miscarriages caused by genetic damage effecting future generations 10 years after, shell casings found in Halabja from Russia, the components from European countries, UN keeping lists secret, interview with Rolf Ekeus denying UN complicity.
  - Part 1: The Road Back to Hell, Part 2: Dispatches - Kurdistan: A Dream Betrayed, Part 3: Dispatches- Winds of Death, PAL VHS [TRT:2:00:00] (Box 317: 3 copies; Box 334: 1 original) (Box 317 and 334, Video-cassette ME017)
    Producer: All 3: Roberts and Wykeham Films for BBC TV
    Original Credits: Par 1: Reporter: Kanan Makiya. Producer: Sadie Wykeham. Filmed and Directed: Gwynne Roberts. Part 2: Reporter: Gwynne Roberts. Producer: Sadie Wykeham. Filmed and Directed: Gwynne Roberts. Part 3: Producer: Sadie Wykeham. Written and Directed: Gwynne Roberts
    Part 1: Writer Kanan Makiya, Iranian opposition figure and his trip back to Iraq, searching for documentary paperwork on Saddam's human rights abuses, documentation captured by Kurdish forces in the North of Iraq, scenes of torture, public executions, with archival footage of chemical attacks on Iraqi Kurds, the Anfal, systematic attempt to destroy the Kurds in Northern Iraq, Ali Hassan al-Majid, cousin of Saddam, 1992.
    Par 2: Documentary of the aftermath of liberation of Iraqi Kurdistan after the end of the Gulf War, return of an exiled Kurd to his homeland, and the situation in the brief period of Kurdish control of northern Iraq, including footage of Halabja. The counterattack of Saddam's troops in 1991 Mar. after the end of Gulf War and recapture of Kirkuk and other Kurdish areas, 1991.
    Part 3: Winds of Death - Search for evidence of gas attacks against Kurds by Iraqi army in 1988 Aug., after the cease fire in the war against Iran. Interviews at refugee camps in Iran with Kurdish refugees and victims of gas attacks, description of suffering by gas victims, including Massoud Barzani, Kurdistan Democratic Party (KDP) leader, and other guerrillas testifying to use of poison gas by Saddam, also includes Iranian footage of gas attack on Halabja and only shots of nerve gas attacks, collection of contaminated soil as evidence, Physicians for Human Rights, and Peter Galbraith, researcher on gas attacks by Iraq by Senate Foreign Relations Committee, 1988.
  - Dispatches: The Saudi Tapes [1997 Feb. 2], NTSC VHS [TRT:0:42:00] (3 copies) (Box 317 and 334, Video-cassette ME018)
    Producer: Gwynne Roberts
    Original Credits: Dispatches-Channel 4 BBC television program
    Reporter Gwynne Roberts goes undercover in Saudi Arabia reporting on the opposition in Saudi Arabia and the story of poverty not know in outside world. Interview with Osama Bin Laden, vows to overthrow the Saudi ruling party, also impact of American presence and influence on the Saudi opposition.
  - Doh Padshaheh, Yek Noshet (Two Kings: One Destiny), NTSC VHS [TRT:0:21:00] (3 copies) (Box 317 and 334, Video-cassette ME019)
    Language: Persian
    Producer: Jaam-E-Jam Productions
    Documentary on Iran late nineteenth century and up to World War II, a lot of archival footage and old photographs, from Qajar times, children's education and work, 1911 revolution, division of Iran by England and Russia, discovery of oil in Iran, influence of Russian revolution, coronation of Reza Shah, change of name to Iran, modernization, visit to Turkey of Reza Shah, no veil policy for women, European education systems.
  - Az Qajar ta Khomeini (From the Qajars to Khomeini) -, NTSC VHS [TRT:1:00:00] (3 copies) (Box 317 and 334, Video-cassette ME020)
    Producer: Jaam-E-Jam Productions of BBC original
    Persian Version of The Last Shah (see also ME50).
    Reworking of BBC Documentary on the Shah of Iran, produced and directed by Tim Kirby, narrated by Ben Kingsley.
    Farhang Farahi Introduction.
    Narrated in Persian by news anchor in style of news report.
    Documentary on Twentieth Century in Iran, history of the Reza family, all main events of Iranian twentieth century history, coup d'etat of Mossadegh era of 1954, student demonstrations, democracy movements, coronation of Pahlavi Shah., torture of prisoners under rule of Shah, footage of Carter visit to Iran, and the revolution.
    A lot of archival footage, including some of Nasr ad-Din Shah and Reza Shah and other historical photos.